<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to the clergy of the diocese of Lincoln by ... James Lord Bishop of that diocese, in order to his primary visitation.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, James, 1637-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G223A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13044924</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13044924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96907</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 739:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to the clergy of the diocese of Lincoln by ... James Lord Bishop of that diocese, in order to his primary visitation.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, James, 1637-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition with additions, corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 35-[1].</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96907:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96907:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ADVICE TO THE CLERGY Of the DIOCESE of LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>JAMES</hi> Lord Biſhop of that Dioceſe.</p>
            <p>In Order to his Primary <hi>VISITATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition with Additions, Corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Everingham,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-ſtreet.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96907:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96907:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Chooſe to take this Method of ſending ſome <hi>Advices</hi> to you before my <hi>Viſitation,</hi> rather than to ſpeak to you on a ſudden at the reſpective places appointed for you to meet at. But becauſe this is a new Method, therefore I think it not improper for me to give you my <hi>Reaſons</hi> for ſo doing; Which are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To make my own Duty and Buſineſs more eaſie to my ſelf, and the better to ſecure my <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> which otherwiſe might be impaired and weakened in 7 or 8 Weeks travailing together, and performing thoſe Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Offices which are requiſite to be performed at the ſeveral places of <hi>Viſitation,</hi> ſo that it may be expected ſome times to happen, that through <hi>wearineſs</hi> or other <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition</hi> (the ſeaſon of the Year being uſually hot, and the places of Viſitation many) I may be hindred from ſpeaking ſo much, and ſo fully, as I might otherwiſe be willing and deſirous to do. Beſides, there is one particular <hi>Office,</hi> viz. that of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which I deſign to take the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of performing in my paſſage from one place of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation to another, at the great <hi>Towns</hi> that lie in, or not far out of my way, of which I intend to give timely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the day and hour, to the Miniſters of ſuch Towns that they may be ready to preſent ſuch Perſons to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, as are within their own, or their neighbouring Pariſhes, which will take up no little of my time and labour.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96907:3"/> II. But I have not regard to my <hi>ſelf</hi> only in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, but to <hi>you</hi> alſo; for by this means ſome that may be hindred from coming to the place of Viſitation, by <hi>Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>very Old Age,</hi> or <hi>unavoidable</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> Buſineſs and Attendance elſewhere, may be acquainted with what I think fit to lay before thoſe that are concerned to appear upon theſe occaſions. Where theſe <hi>Excuſes</hi> are <hi>unfeigned,</hi> they are <hi>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and thoſe that are forced to uſe them, by having this Paper of <hi>Advice</hi> by them, may <hi>ſee</hi> what I have to propoſe as well as they might have <hi>heard</hi> it, if it had been <hi>ſpoken,</hi> and they themſelves preſent. But I hope that none, but thoſe that are ſo <hi>indiſpoſed,</hi> as I now mentioned, will abſent themſelves.</p>
            <p>For as it is the <hi>Duty</hi> of a Biſhop to <hi>Viſit,</hi> ſo it is the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Clergy to appear at ſuch <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> where the <hi>Viſitation</hi> is appointed. Thoſe <hi>Pretences</hi> that cannot <hi>excuſe</hi> a Biſhop, before God, and the Church, and his own Conſcience, from <hi>Viſiting,</hi> can leſs <hi>excuſe</hi> the Clergy of his Dioceſe from <hi>appearing.</hi> A Biſhop may ordinarily alledge his <hi>Age,</hi> and the <hi>Indiſpoſition</hi> that uſually attends it, <hi>Debility</hi> of Body and Voice; The hazards of Health by continual motion, it may be, in ill Weather, not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently accommodated, and for many Weeks together; ſo that a Biſhop, eſpecially in this Dioceſe, that would ſtudy his <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>health</hi> more than his <hi>obligation,</hi> might colour his Omiſſion by theſe, and the like Pleas, and ſatisfy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with being <hi>quiet</hi> at his own Habitation; But the Clergy of the Dioceſe, except the very <hi>aged</hi> and <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> cannot in like manner excuſe themſelves for their Omiſſion; The <hi>weakeſt</hi> may have Strength enough for one days Journey, without running any hazard, and for the <hi>Younger</hi> and more <hi>healthful,</hi> which are the greater Number, they have ſo little to ſay in excuſe of themſelves, that one would be apt to think that their abſence proceeded either from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96907:3"/>Sloth, or Envy, or Prejudice, or, it may be, ſome Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical or Political Principle, for what elſe can hinder them?</p>
            <p>Nay, may they not propoſe to themſelves many things that may induce and incourage them to come? They may be preſent at the preaching of a <hi>Sermon</hi> fitted and prepared for the occaſion of their Meeting; They may have an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſeeing ſeveral of their diſtant Friends and Acquaintance; They may contract Acquaintance with ſuch as are but newly entred into the Neghbourhood; They may oblige one another in ſtricter Ties of Brotherly Love; They may animate one another in the faithful diſcharge of their Office; They may excite one another's Zeal and Fervency in promoting the ſame common Intereſt of the Chriſtian Religion; They may direct one another in the Knowledge of Modern Books and Treatiſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; They may enter into combined Reſolutions to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in its <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip, and Government,</hi> as it is eſtabliſhed, againſt all Parties that divide from it; They may incourage one another to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vigorouſly the <hi>Vices</hi> and the <hi>Factions</hi> of the Age, and to advance Holineſs and Peace and Submiſſion to Authority; In a word, They may let this <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> and deluded Age ſee that they are unanimouſly bent to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> to purſue the <hi>Service,</hi> and to promote the <hi>Honour</hi> of the bleſſed Saviour of the World, whoſe <hi>Servants</hi> they are and whoſe work and buſineſs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling Men to God they have avowedly undertaken; If the Clergy were ſenſible that they might attain to theſe good Ends by meeting their <hi>Dioceſan</hi> at his <hi>Viſitation,</hi> what conſidering Man would abſent himſelf? So that I hope the ſending of this <hi>Advice</hi> to be read, and to lie by you, will be ſo far from hindring you from coming to the Viſitation, that it will rather prevail with you to come; and I hope that the ſerious and deliberate peruſal of it may be of more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96907:4"/>Uſe and Benefit than a tranſient Diſcourſe; for I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that ſometimes ſuch Diſcourſes have not been heard by all preſent, either by reaſon of the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Voice, or the <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>talk</hi> which may occaſionally happen; or if they have been heard, they have been ſoon forgotten, ſo that many profitable Inſtructions have been dropt and loſt; whereas, by this way, they may not only be communicated to all, but alſo be preſerved and reviewed upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>And now having given you the Motives that induced me to tranſmit theſe <hi>Adviſes</hi> from the Preſs, rather than to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them at our Meeting, I ſhall proceed to hint ſuch Things, as by your kind and unprejudiced Reception of them, may, with God's bleſſing, make this Viſitation uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Ends for which it is deſigned.</p>
            <p>Which, in General, is to know the State of this Dioceſe, to ſee how all Perſons behave themſelves in it, with reſpect to their ſeveral Duties either as Chriſtians in general, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Church of Chriſt, or Subjects of the Civil Government. For Epiſcopal Viſitation has an Eye both to the Clergy and
<note n="*" place="margin">Inſtrument of Inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Clerum &amp;</hi>
               </note> Laity, but principally to the Clergy, to whoſe Cure and Conduct, in order to their eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the
<note n="*" place="margin">Populum.</note> Laity are commited.</p>
            <p>This is a vaſt Buſineſs in this large Dioceſe, and requires great diligence, and application of mind; and I have often been much concerned and grieved, that I want that <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> of which the Conſtitution, and external Regiment and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Church has been provided; I mean, The <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of <hi>Rural Deans,</hi> which Office is a part of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and is yet exerciſed in ſome Dioceſes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but has unhappily been diſuſed in this, (for how long time I know not) to the great loſs and hindrance of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Adminiſtration.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96907:4"/>
            <p> By the impartial and diligent Execution of this <hi>Office,</hi> the Biſhop might be eaſed in a great part of that Duty, which is too heavy a Burthen for his own Shoulders; The Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the Factious, the Scandalous, the Negligent, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, might eaſily be detected in a ſmall <hi>Deanary;</hi> and being ſignified to the Biſhop, or rather firſt of all and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the <hi>Arch-Deacon,</hi> might be timely and duely corrected, and reformed; For the Arch-deacon inhabiting within his Arch-deaconry, as it is moſt proper, might eaſily be reſorted to upon occaſion, and ſo Hear and Amend many Faults, which might be brought to him by the <hi>Rural Dean,</hi> without Application to the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>If a Biſhop of this extenſive Dioceſe was provided of active and faithful Perſons in the ſeveral <hi>Deanries,</hi> which retain the name yet, his Buſineſs might be manageable, and his Authority and Government uſeful, whereas for want of theſe, no Biſhop here can do ſo much and ſo well as he might be willing and glad to do.</p>
            <p>But in the defect of theſe <hi>Aſſiſtances,</hi> it is in your Power, My Brethren, to give me eaſe and ſatisfaction in my weak Endeavours. If you would do what you have declared, and promiſed, and reſolved to do in the preſence of God and the Congregation at your Ordination, it would diſcharge me of a great deal of care and trouble.</p>
            <p>Where there is a formed and ſettled Church, as this of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is, with known Rules and Meaſures, by which the Clergy are bound to exerciſe their Miniſtry, one would think, if Men were ſincere, they could not fail in performing this part of their duty, for they cannot, or, at leaſt, they need not be ignorant of the Obligations that are laid upon them, by the Laws of the Kingdom, and the Canons of the Church, not to mention here the <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations</hi> that they have laid upon themſelves; But it is too true that there is a <hi>Failure</hi> in ſome Perſons as to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96907:5"/>of thoſe Obligations, which if it be frequent and habitual can proceed from nothing but <hi>Prejudice,</hi> or <hi>Sloath,</hi> or <hi>Inconſideration,</hi> in all which there is a ſpice of <hi>Inſincerity.</hi> I know ſome will plead want of <hi>Health,</hi> and others an Obligation to officiate in ſeveral places for a bare Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency: But one may eaſily diſtinguiſh whether theſe be the <hi>true</hi> Reaſons, or whether their Omiſſions proceed from other cauſes; To be ſure, they themſelves know; I wiſh their Pretences were always ſincere; However the unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Negligence</hi> of ſome, and the <hi>Immoralities</hi> of others are the ſubjects of the Biſhop's <hi>Trouble</hi> and <hi>Inquiry.</hi> If there were none ſuch, a Biſhop's Viſitation would be eaſie and comfortable.</p>
            <p>It would have been well if ſuch Perſons had been ſtopt at the firſt <hi>door,</hi> that of <hi>Ordination,</hi> but having been let in there, where the door was too wide, they are the Men that make the greateſt diſorder and trouble within. If theſe Men had come ſo <hi>diſpoſed</hi> and <hi>qualified</hi> into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Church as they profeſſed themſelves to be, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming at their Ordination, that they <hi>truſted they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly moved by the Holy Ghoſt to take upon them the Office and Miniſtration of Deacons to ſerve God for the promoting of his Glory and the edifying of his People;</hi> They would behave themſelves after another manner; whereas practiſing ſo diſagreeably to that <hi>Declaration</hi> they made, they give occaſion to the World to believe that it was a falſe and groundleſs <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and a ſort of <hi>Lying againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Or elſe, that if they had any ſuch good <hi>Motion,</hi> they have <hi>quenched</hi> it ſince by their unworthy and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Behaviour.</p>
            <p>If ſuch Men would bethink themſelves, and reflect upon the ſolemn Profeſſion, Promiſe, and Vow which they made at their Ordination, it might be a means to revive that holy Fire within them, (if it was ever kindled in their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96907:5"/>Hearts) which they have ſo heedleſly extinguiſh'd. I would for that reaſon adviſe them frequently and delib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to read the Offices of Ordaining Deacons and Prieſts, where they may ſee not only their <hi>Work</hi> laid out and ſet before them, with the <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> of it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Obligation</hi> they have laid upon themſelves to perform it, and if there be any <hi>Ingenuity</hi> remaining in them agreeable to their <hi>Liberal</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Education, any <hi>Senſe</hi> of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, any <hi>Regard</hi> to the Love of Chriſt and his Church, any <hi>Hope</hi> of reward for their due attendance to their Duty, any <hi>Fear</hi> of the extreme Puniſhment that will certainly follow upon the neglect of it, it cannot but affect them with <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>trouble,</hi> which would awaken within them ſervent <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> and hearty <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> and careful <hi>Endeavours</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge then Obligations for the future.</p>
            <p>And if there be any that have entred into Orders without <hi>feeling,</hi> or <hi>pretending</hi> to feel any ſuch ſecret <hi>motion</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, but ſolely for ſecular Ends and Advantages, however they have made a falſe ſtep at their Entrance, they may yet recover themſelves, if by ſerious and timely <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> and begging the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of the Holy Spirit, (who preſides in, and takes care of the Church of Chriſt, and is ready to Co-operate with thoſe that ſerve the Lord Jeſus in the Work of the Miniſtry) they could be prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, out of an <hi>hearty</hi> ſenſe of their Duty, to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>diligently</hi> to the practice of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Natural Faculties and Abilities, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of which would prevail with God to beſtow more and greater.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the beſt and moſt proper <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> for the work of the Miniſtry in the Church of Chriſt is <hi>Simplicity</hi> and <hi>Sincerity</hi> of Heart. This <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> our Saviour preferred in the Election of His Apoſtles, excepting only one whom he choſe for a particular reaſon. Men thus qualified will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96907:6"/>ſerve their Maſter Faithfully in all Circumſtances, and be the outward condition of the Church either <hi>Afflicted</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous,</hi> they will be true to the Intereſt of it, <hi>knowing how to be abaſed and how to abound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Church of Chriſt was provided of Miniſters ſo <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified</hi> in all places, the Viſitation of a Biſhop would be no Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then either to himſelf or them. It was ſo provided in the firſt Ages after the Apoſtles; And in the ſucceeding Ages, during the time of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> to the time of the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> this Nation produced not a few Perſons very illuſtrious and eminent in this Character: I ſhall do no wrong to many others to inſtance in one particularly, a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Robert Groft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of this Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, who amongſt many other excellent Indowments, both natural and acquired, was eſpecially remarkt for <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Probity;</hi> This made him Magnanimous, reſolute and fervent, in reſiſting and oppugning the corrupt Practiſes of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> altho it expoſed him to the neglects and cenſures of that <hi>Court,</hi> notwithſtanding he was the greateſt Man of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Induſtry</hi> in that Age.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> began and carried on the Reformation in the Weſtern parts of Chriſtendom in a wonderful manner, through many difficulties and hazards. It was indeed an happy <hi>Direction</hi> of Providence that at the ſame <hi>juncture,</hi> many of thoſe <hi>upright</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> Reformers, were alſo Men of better <hi>Capacity</hi> and better <hi>Learning</hi> than the common Romiſh Clergy; and where <hi>Learning</hi> is joyned with <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Simplicity,</hi> there can be no better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment for the Work of the Miniſtry. The preſent Age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with many Helps and Aſſiſtances of Learning, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> is provided of many Clergymen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently <hi>Learned:</hi> I will not accuſe any of want of <hi>Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> but I am apt to think that if that was generally the reigning and governing <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> in the Clergy, there would be leſſer need of Inquiry and Reformation than I doubt there is.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96907:6"/>
            <p> This would make them <hi>careful</hi> to obſerve the Vows and Promiſes they made at their Ordination; This would make Rectors and Vicars <hi>tender</hi> of thoſe <hi>Souls</hi> who are committed to their Cure at their
<note n="*" place="margin">Form of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Parochia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum tibi in Domino committimus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> This would make Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates <hi>Sollicitous</hi> for the Flock with which they are intruſted, although they have not Inſtitution; This would reſtrain all ſorts from the immoderate purſuit of <hi>Pluralities,</hi> and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them to <hi>Reſidence,</hi> making it acceptable and delightful to them; This would ingage all the <hi>Ranks</hi> of the Clergy to be <hi>zealous</hi> and <hi>earneſt</hi> in regaining the <hi>Seduced,</hi> and reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Vicious,</hi> and improving <hi>all.</hi> This is that ſalt which not only preſerves the Clergy from Corruption, but alſo ſeaſons all their Performances. In ſhort, this makes them acceptable to God, and uſeful to the Church; This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that Grace or Diſpoſition of Mind, which you ſhould beg of God to beſtow upon you, and uſe your greateſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to acquire; which if you be indowed with, it will appear not only in the Holineſs of your Lives as you are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but alſo in the Faithful performance of your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as you are <hi>Clergymen.</hi> This I ſhall make evident by inſtancing in the <hi>Principal</hi> Offices which your Holy <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> does oblige you to perform.</p>
            <p>The firſt of which is <hi>Prayer,</hi> by which I mean the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liturgy</hi> of the Church. To this you have promiſed to <hi>conform,</hi> and ſubſcribed your Hands to that Promiſe; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the 2d of the 3 <hi>Articles</hi> mentioned in the 36th Canon. <hi>That the Book of Common Proyer containeth in it, nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God, and that you your ſelves will uſe the Form in the ſaid Book preſcribed, in publick Prayer, and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, and none other.</hi> Does he make good theſe <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> who reads the Common Prayer very <hi>ſeldom,</hi> or not in <hi>order,</hi> or not the <hi>whole,</hi> but only ſome parts and peices, or if he do read the whole, reads it ſo <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily,</hi> or ſo <hi>ſlightly</hi> and <hi>awkwardly</hi> as that an impartial Hearer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96907:7"/>might be apt to think that he had no good liking to it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas</hi> a Man that is <hi>ſincere</hi> and in good earneſt in this partof Religious Worſhip would be careful to read it, <hi>lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. 1559.</note> 
               <hi>plainly</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. 1559.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinctly,</hi> well remembring that he addreſſes himſelf, as the Mouth and Leader of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to that God who knows, and who requires the Heart in all ſuch Services; He would alſo uſe his beſt Endeavour to read with ſuch <hi>proper</hi> and becoming <hi>Tone</hi> and <hi>Accent</hi> as may beſt excite <hi>attention, affection,</hi> and <hi>fervour</hi> in himſelf &amp; others.</p>
            <p>There is indeed a natural Indiſpoſition in ſome Men to all kind of vocal Harmony, even to that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts only in the <hi>Elevation</hi> and <hi>Depreſſion</hi> of the Voice in proper places and periods; I call them <hi>proper,</hi> not only with regard to the art of Muſic, but even to the ſence of the Words; But I ſhall not urge this further than the natural capacity of men will bear; There is certainly a <hi>felicity</hi> in Voice and Accent, which they ought to make good uſe of to whom God has given it, and thoſe that want it, can only uſe their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to attain to ſuch a degree, as to avoid at leaſt all groſs, abſurd, and ridiculous pronunciation.</p>
            <p>But ſuch as do not think this worthy their Labouring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I am ſure they cannot excuſe themſelves in <hi>neglecting, omitting,</hi> or <hi>altering</hi> any part of the publick Offices; And though they read them not with that propriety of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterance</hi> and <hi>Accent</hi> which may promote attention and devotion, they ought at leaſt to perform the Offices as they are directed and preſcribed, for nothing leſs than this can Anſwer their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, which will remain in the Biſhops Cuſtody as a witneſs of their <hi>Inſincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is to be underſtood not only of the Offices of Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening Prayer, (which if they could be daily performed in all Pariſhes would be of great uſe to breed in Peoples minds a ſenſe of their dependance upon God from day to day) but alſo all Occaſional Offices, the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96907:7"/>of the <hi>Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, Matrimony, the Viſitation of the Sick, and Burial of the Dead.</hi> All theſe ought to be performed <hi>ſeriouſly, ſolemnly,</hi> and <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately,</hi> and in the expreſſions and order in which they are directed, which can only ſatisfy the <hi>Conformity</hi> which you have promiſed.</p>
            <p>As to one of theſe Offices, that of <hi>publick Baptiſm of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> I muſt adviſe you to uſe your utmoſt Endeavour to prevail with your Pariſhioners to bring their Children to Church to be Baptized, and not feign Pretences for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them baptized at their own Houſes; or, if there be a real Danger, and that Sickneſs, <hi>or other need compels them ſo to do,</hi> if the Child live, you muſt not fail to admoniſh them that it is <hi>expedient</hi> (as the Rubrick directs) to bring the Child to Church afterwards. This is a part of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which you have ſubſcribed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add one Word more upon this Subject, which is the Obſervation of the <hi>Faſts</hi> and <hi>Feaſts</hi> of the Church which are directed in the Books of Common Prayer; the neglect of which has proceeded, in ſome places, as much from the Miniſter, as from the People; the Miniſter is to give notice of all ſuch Days; and why is that? But that the People may know that ſuch Days being appointed for the more than <hi>ordinary</hi> Worſhip and Service of God, they ought to forbear their <hi>Labour and Work,</hi> at leaſt at the Hours of Worſhip, and repair to Church, where, if there be no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to officiate, to what purpoſe ſhould they come? This is an unaccountable Neglect and ſavours of <hi>Inſincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from that part of your Duty which relates to God, as you lead and conduct your Congregation in the Offices of Publick Worſhip, I proceed to that part of your Duty which relates to the <hi>Congregation,</hi> as you are to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them; And this comprehends <hi>Reading</hi> the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Preaching, Catechiſing, oppoſing all Erroneous and Strange Doctrines contrary to Gods Word, uſing publick and private Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96907:8"/>and Exhortations as well to the Sick as to the Poo within your Cures, as need ſhall require, and occaſion be given.</hi> As it is in the Offices of the Ordering of Prieſts, to which ſuch as are ordained Prieſts have promiſed <hi>to be ready to do with all faithful Diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Doctrinal and Inſtructive part of your Duty as it reſpects Men; and the <hi>Rule</hi> of this Performance is the Holy Scriptures; for you have declared at your Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that you were <hi>Perſuaded that the Holy Scriptures contain ſufficiently all Doctrine required of neceſſity for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation through Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; and that you were determined out of the ſaid Scriptures to inſtruct the People committed to your Charge, and to teach nothing (as required of neceſſity to Eternal Salvation) but that which you ſhall be perſwaded may be concluded and proved by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> The Miniſters of the Goſpel are the Miniſters of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion, as were the <hi>Prophets</hi> under the Law from <hi>Moſes</hi> the great <hi>Prophet</hi> till the ceaſing of Prophecy; the ſtanding <hi>Revelation</hi> which God has made to mankind is contained in the Scripture, which is therefore called the <hi>Word</hi> of God; and it is our Buſineſs to <hi>Study,</hi> to <hi>Read</hi> and to <hi>Explain</hi> this.</p>
            <p>All Chriſtians indeed are bound to <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> the Scriptures ſo far as they are capable; but all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are not bound to <hi>Read</hi> and to <hi>Explain</hi> them <hi>publickly</hi> in Chriſtian Aſſemblies; Nay they are bound not to do it, unleſs they be <hi>Separated</hi> and <hi>Appointed</hi> thereto by proper Authority; becauſe our Saviour at the firſt Founding and Erecting his Kingdom did <hi>Separate</hi> Men for this purpoſe, and did require ſuch a <hi>Separation</hi> to be continued ſo long as his Kingdom ſhould continue upon Earth, it being neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the uſeful Ends of <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Edification,</hi> and the <hi>Salvation</hi> of the Souls of Men.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96907:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Now</hi> this <hi>Separation</hi> is made at <hi>Ordination,</hi> by which there is a general Authority or Commiſſion given <hi>to Read</hi> and <hi>to Preach the Goſpel;</hi> but not every where, or in all, or in any place, or at any times, or to any Congregation or Society of Chriſtians, as the Ordained Perſon pleaſes; this is impracticable, and would occaſion great Diſorder and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; But it is limited to certain
<note n="*" place="margin">In the office of ordering of Deacons. <hi>If thou be thereto Licenſed by the Biſhop himſelf.</hi> In the office of ordering of Prieſts. <hi>In the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where thou ſhalt be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed thereunto.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conditions,</hi> of which <hi>Licenſing</hi> is one; And this gives me occaſion to ſpeak of <hi>Licenſing</hi> to Preach, which ſome Men are prone to cenſure as an unneceſſary Impoſition upon the Clergy; and here I ſhall offer ſomething, firſt concerning the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing. 2ly, Concerning the <hi>Perſon</hi> who is to <hi>Licenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of Licenſing; By the
<note n="*" place="margin">Canon XLV. Singuli Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiati in Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis ſuis reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes (dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſint le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitima Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate admiſſi) per ſingulos, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Canon XLVI. Omnis Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiatus ad Concionan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſus, Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem per Concionato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem legitime approbatum haberi procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Canons of 1603. it appears that all <hi>Beneficed Men</hi> were not allowed to be <hi>Preachers</hi> I take it that <hi>Beneficed Men</hi> are ſuch as have <hi>Inſtitution</hi> to <hi>Benefices,</hi> ſo that in the Judgment of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> by which that Body of Canons was compiled, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> alone did not Authorize Men to be <hi>Preachers,</hi> But <hi>Preachers</hi> were to be <hi>Licenſed;</hi> therefore there is a <hi>Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of Licenſing even as to <hi>Beneficed</hi> Men; And though there is not (God be thanked) that <hi>real</hi> Neceſſity that, it may be, there was at the time of that <hi>Convocation</hi> ſitting, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſince then a general increaſe of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge;</hi> Yet ſtill there is a <hi>neceſſity</hi> as to the obſervation of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and a great <hi>Expediency,</hi> if it was more uſed, as to the regulating of <hi>Preaching,</hi> which, within the compaſs of our own Obſervation and Experience, has been made an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument,</hi> not only of promoting <hi>Error</hi> in the Church, but alſo <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtitution</hi> then does not authorize <hi>Beneficed</hi> Men to preach in their own <hi>Benefices</hi> unlicenſed; ſo that if neither <hi>Ordination,</hi> nor <hi>Inſtitution</hi> give ſufficient Authority to preach, I mean, as to particular Dioceſes and Churches,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96907:9"/>without <hi>Licence,</hi> then there is a neceſſity of <hi>Licenſing</hi> all <hi>Preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it ſhould be granted that <hi>Institution</hi> does authorize a Clerk to <hi>Preach,</hi> it can be only in that <hi>Benefice</hi> to which he is <hi>Inſtituted,</hi> and where he has
<note n="*" place="margin">Inſtrument of Inſtitution.</note> 
               <hi>curam Animarum Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chianorum,</hi> not in any part of the Dioceſe or Archdeacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſides; and therefore ſtill there is a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> to enable Men to <hi>Preach</hi> in other Churches of the Neighbourhood, or in other parts of the Archdeaconry, or Dioceſe, as there may ſometimes be occaſion, by the <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary</hi> Supply of other Men's Cures, upon <hi>Abſence,</hi> or <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> or <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> of the Incumbent, or <hi>Voydance</hi> by <hi>Reſignation, Deprivation,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> which ſort of Supply an <hi>unlicenſed</hi> Man ought not to undertake. So that it is very evident, that there is a <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or at leaſt a great Expediency, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring <hi>Preachers</hi> to be <hi>Licenſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>II.</hi> As to the Perſon who is to <hi>Licence,</hi> it is only the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſe <hi>himſelf,</hi> in which the <hi>Licenſed</hi> Perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. This as to <hi>Deacons</hi> ſeem, very plain by theſe Words in the Office of <hi>Ordination,</hi> which the Biſhop uſes in the Delivery of the New Teſtament to the <hi>ordained</hi> Perſon. <hi>Take thou Authority to Read the Goſpel in the Church of God, and to Preach the ſame if thou be thereto</hi> Licenſed <hi>by the Biſhop <hi>himſelf.</hi>
               </hi> Which I take to be the Biſhop of the Dioceſe where the <hi>ordained</hi> Perſon has a <hi>Title</hi> to officiate; and therefore if a Biſhop of one Dioceſs, by vertue of <hi>Letters Dimiſſory,</hi> ordain a Deacon who has a Title in another Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, that Biſhop, in whoſe Dioceſe the <hi>Title</hi> is, ought to grant the <hi>Licence,</hi> and not the ordaining Biſhop.</p>
            <p>But that for which I mention this, principally is, That the <hi>Licence</hi> is to be granted by the <hi>Biſhop <hi>himſelf:</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96907:9"/>
            <p> This addition or limitation being made at the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Forms of Ordaining Deacons, Prieſts, and Biſhops were purged and altered. It was then judged re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to reſtrain the Authority of Licenſing Readers and Preachers to the Biſhop himſelf, knowing what ill uſe had been made by the Eccleſiaſtical Officers before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they being then under no reſtraint for granting ſuch Licences, ſo that this limitation was made on purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain any other Officer, or ſubſtitute.</p>
            <p>And as to <hi>Deacons,</hi> ſo alſo to <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as it ſeems evident by the xxxvi and xxxvii Canons. The xxxvi <hi>Canon</hi> requires <hi>Subſcription</hi> to the 3 Articles there mentioned before Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The xxxvii. <hi>Canon</hi> Requires, that notwithſtanding the general Power given to the ordained Perſon at his <hi>Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> when he comes to Reſide in any Dioceſe, he ſhall not be permitted there to <hi>preach,</hi> &amp;c. unleſs he firſt conſent and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the ſaid 3 Articles, <hi>in the Preſence of the Biſhop of the Dioceſe</hi> wherein he is to <hi>Preach,</hi> &amp;c. It is ſaid in the <hi>preſence of the Biſhop;</hi> It is not ſaid of the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> for ſo the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour</hi> of the Dioceſs may be, but of the <hi>Biſhop:</hi> And that by the Biſhop here is meant, the Biſhop only excluſive of any Eccleſiaſtical Officers is plain by the 48 Canon, where it is thus ordained. <hi>No Curate or Miniſter ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſerve in any place without Examination and Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Biſhop of the Dioceſe, or Ordinary of the Place, having Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, in writing under his Hand and Seal, having reſpect to the greatneſs of the Cure, and Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Perſon.</hi> Where it is to be obſerved, 1. That it is ſaid no <hi>Curate or Miniſter,</hi> which I take to include all the Licenſed Clergy, and may be urged further in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of what I ſaid before concerning thoſe that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96907:10"/>have Inſtitution, as well as thoſe that have not. 2. That <hi>Admiſſion</hi> to ſerve Curacies is to be in Writing under the <hi>Hand and Seal of the Biſhop,</hi> and if the Eccleſiaſtical Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Seal may be alledged to be the Biſhops Seal, his Hand cannot be ſaid to be the Biſhops Hand. 3. That <hi>Examination</hi> ought to precede this <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop may Judge of the <hi>Meetneſs</hi> of the Party, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Officer imployed in this matter is not qualified to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. 4. That no Man <hi>ſhall be permitted to ſerve in any place,</hi> but one that is thus <hi>examined and admitted by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Ordinary of the Place having Epiſcopal Juriſdiction.</hi> By the <hi>Ordinary of the Place</hi> cannot be meant the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Dioceſe, but ſuch Ordinaries as have Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Juriſdiction by virtue of ſome Ancient Grant from, or Compoſition with the Biſhop, ſuch as Deans, Deans and Chapters, ſole Prebendaries, and, it may be, others, in the Ancient Foundations, who have a Right to exerciſe <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction</hi> in the Peculiars belonging to their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, which is very well known in the Church of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi> particularly; Theſe are the Ordinaries of the Place here meant. And the Biſhop and ſuch Ordinaries have the ſole Authority of granting Licences to Preach and ſerve Cures under their Hands and Scals.</p>
            <p>Purſuant to this, is the 8th Article in his Majeſties late Injunctions, where it is required, <hi>That they who keep Curates have none but ſuch as are Licenſed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſe, or in exempt Juriſdictions by the Ordinary of the Place having Epiſcopal Juriſdiction—and that no Perſon ſhall preſume to ſerve any Cure without Licence from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or ſuch Ordinary, upon pain of ſuſpenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96907:10"/>
            <p> So that the Form of Ordination, which is confirmed by the Act of Uniformity, the Canons, the Kings Injunctions, all agree in this, that no one can Licence Perſons to Preach or ſerve Cures, but the Biſhop of the Dioceſe himſelf, or ſuch as have Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars, and exempt Places. This I take notice of that the Clergy may not be impoſed upon, by <hi>falſe, inſufficient</hi> and <hi>uncanonical</hi> Licences, as I know too many are; And to ſhew the great Care that the Church has taken, that the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of every Dioceſe, may know the <hi>Clergy</hi> of his Dioceſe, their <hi>Character</hi> and their <hi>Abilities</hi> to preach, and be ſatisfied of their <hi>Orders</hi> and their <hi>Converſation,</hi> which he cannot be, if Eccleſiaſtical Officers may grant <hi>Licences,</hi> eſpecially upon <hi>Sequestrations</hi> of vacant Livings, and <hi>Supply</hi> of <hi>Curates</hi> and <hi>Lecturers,</hi> at their pleaſure. How can the Biſhop tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men ſo <hi>Licenſed</hi> have Subſcribed to the 3 Articles men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the forecited xxxvi Canon, eſpecially if the <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> keep no Book of Subſcriptions, or make no Return to the Biſhop of them, as ſome do not? Or indeed, how can the Biſhop tell whether ſuch <hi>Licenſed Men</hi> be ordained, or how they have behaved themſelves in the place of their laſt Reſidence?</p>
            <p>Where ſuch Power is aſſumed, any <hi>illiterate, corrupt</hi> or <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Surrogate</hi> may grant <hi>Licences</hi> to unordained, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified, and inſufficient Men, and the Biſhop never know it. Many ſmall Livings are held only by <hi>Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration;</hi> and if the Serving of the Cure, together with the power of Sequeſtring the Profits be granted at the pleaſure of the Surrogate, the Biſhop not knowing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Men may eaſily get into Curacys, and if they can but ſcreen themſelves at the Times of Viſitation, they may continue undiſcovered.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96907:11"/>
            <p> This is a Practice of very ill <hi>Conſequence;</hi> for Preaching the Word of God, comprehending as before mentioned, is not to be intruſted but to Men well <hi>qualified</hi> for their <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the Holy Scriptures; And the Biſhop, who has the firſt care in this matter, ought to be ſatisfied that they are ſo, and particularly of <hi>Curates,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they officiate by virtue of <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> in vacant Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or under <hi>Beneficed</hi> Men, who by reaſon of their <hi>Age</hi> or <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> or <hi>Neceſſary</hi> abſence, or being poſſeſſed of two <hi>Benefices,</hi> ſtand in need of ſuch <hi>Aſſiſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having ſaid thus much as to the <hi>Authority</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for publick <hi>Preaching,</hi> and the due and legal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Exerciſe of it by the <hi>Biſhop himſelf</hi> in granting <hi>Licences;</hi> I return to what I hinted concerning the <hi>Subject Matter</hi> to which your <hi>Preaching</hi> is reſtrained, which is the <hi>Word of God.</hi> This is that <hi>Storehouſe</hi> which contains all things neceſſary to be believed and practiſed, ſo that all the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and all the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> are to be drawn from hence. The <hi>Fundamental</hi> Articles ought to be explained carefully and evidently from proper Texts of Scripture, the <hi>Belief</hi> of them being neceſſary to eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; I heſe may be handled conveniently upon the great <hi>Feſtivals,</hi> and other <hi>Holy Days</hi> in which we celebrate thoſe more illuſtrious parts of our Saviour's Hiſtory, of which we profeſs the Belief as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> But at all other Seaſons the practical Heads of the Chriſtian Religion are the propereſt <hi>Subjects</hi> for the Pulpit, and there is leſs danger of miſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and miſrepreſenting theſe, eſpecially if one read the Scriptures with that <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>plain</hi> intention of which I have been ſpeaking; otherwiſe many Expreſſions there uſed may be wreſted to ſupport <hi>erroneous</hi> Opinions, and countenance <hi>evil</hi> Practiſes, as we have ſeen and ſtill ſee in the preſent Age. Men bring their <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96907:11"/>with them to the reading of the Scriptures, and then they will not fail to find <hi>them</hi> there, and if they think they find <hi>them</hi> there, they preſume they may vent <hi>them</hi> openly and confidently, and produce that <hi>Holy Book</hi> to <hi>vindicate</hi> them, out of which it is much eaſier to <hi>confute</hi> them.</p>
            <p>God forbid that we ſhould take that courſe to Remedy this, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does, by locking up the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a Language unknown to the unlearned, and to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the Reading of it; or that we ſhould draw ſo wicked an <hi>Inference</hi> from hence, as to <hi>argue,</hi> or but <hi>think,</hi> that becauſe ſo many <hi>ſenceleſs, abſurd,</hi> and <hi>irrational,</hi> as well as <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>blaſphemous</hi> Errors have been pretended to be drawn out of this <hi>Fountain,</hi> that therefore it cannot be the <hi>Word</hi> and Revelation of God, but a corrupt mixture of humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions; No, ſuch men bring their <hi>Poyſon</hi> with them, they do not find it there; If they did partake of that <hi>Spirit</hi> by which it was <hi>indited,</hi> they could make no ſuch ill uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Now this being that <hi>Book</hi> which you, <hi>My Brethren,</hi> are authorized to <hi>Read</hi> and to <hi>explain</hi> publickly, you ſhould not only <hi>ſtudy</hi> it <hi>diligently,</hi> and with great <hi>caution</hi> and <hi>reverence,</hi> but with the like honeſt and ſincere <hi>Intention</hi> which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Writers</hi> had in penning it, conſidering the gracious End for which this <hi>Revelation</hi> was made by God, namely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>implant his <hi>Image</hi> in men, conſiſting in <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity,</hi> which was defaced by <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and rendring them capable of a better and more glorious Immortality than that they have loſt. For this purpoſe the <hi>Law</hi> of God was given, and holy <hi>Prophets</hi> ſent into the World, and at laſt the <hi>Great Prophet</hi> of all, the <hi>Eternal Son of God.</hi> And for this purpoſe did he Erect his <hi>Kingdom</hi> upon Earth, and appoint <hi>Stewards</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> to Miniſter in it; And for this purpoſe were you <hi>Ordained</hi> and <hi>Separated</hi> that you might carry on that great and charitable Work of Redeeming and Saving Mankind.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96907:12"/>
            <p> The Deliberate Conſideration of this would excite in you an <hi>eager</hi> and <hi>fervent</hi> Deſire to have as great a Share as you could in this moſt charitable and God-like Undertaking.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt was erected in Oppoſition to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Sathan, who is ſtiled in Scripture <hi>the Prince of this World;</hi> Your Buſineſs is to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> and <hi>Countermine</hi> him, and all his <hi>Stratagems.</hi> This you cannot do but by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſcharge of that Truſt which is repoſed in you as the <hi>Servants</hi> of Chriſt in adminiſtring and promoting his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I muſt charge upon you, That you deliver faithfully the whole <hi>Law</hi> of Chriſt, by which the <hi>Church</hi> is to be <hi>Inſtructed, Edified</hi> and <hi>Governed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Laws</hi> of Chriſt's Kingdom comprehend not only the eternal and immutable <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but alſo ſome <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>ritual</hi> inſtances which Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>inſtituted</hi> here upon Earth for the neceſſary conduct and management of his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Theſe are the Two <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> The firſt is the Rite of <hi>Initiation</hi> or <hi>Admiſſion</hi> into the Church of Chriſt. The ſecond is the Rite of <hi>Communion</hi> or <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with Chriſt in his Church, whereby <hi>Baptiſed</hi> Perſons, by the <hi>Diſtribution</hi> and <hi>Reception</hi> of Bread and Wine, conſecrated in Memory of the Death of Chriſt, are made Partakers of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe are great and valuable <hi>Privileges,</hi> and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar <hi>Rites</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and you are intruſted with the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe have been moſt ſcandalouſly and prophanely neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by ſome that pretend themſelves to be the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt; eſpecially that of the <hi>Lord's Supper;</hi> for inſtead of <hi>inviting</hi> and <hi>exhorting</hi> Chriſtians to be Partakers at the <hi>Lord's Table,</hi> they have made it their great Endeavour to <hi>deter</hi> them from it; in which they dealt very <hi>unfaithfully</hi> with the Souls
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96907:12"/>of their Hearets; for they vehemently inculcated the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>unworthy Receiving,</hi> without acquainting them with to Danger of not <hi>Receiving</hi> at all; This <hi>Omiſſion</hi> you muſt be careful to <hi>Supply,</hi> and to ſet before the People committed the your charge the <hi>Danger</hi> on both hands; for certainly the prophane <hi>Neglect</hi> in not <hi>Receiving,</hi> is as <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> as the Receiving <hi>unworthily;</hi> for as they are no <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who are not <hi>baptiſed</hi> into the Name of Chriſt, ſo they are no <hi>good</hi> Chriſtians who neglect to partake of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things you ſhould <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Exhort,</hi> and thereby ſhew your ſelves faithful to your Lord and Maſter, who has ordained theſe Two <hi>Sacraments</hi> to be perpetually uſed and adminiſtred in the Church until his coming again.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe as there is in every Church a <hi>Font</hi> for <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſo there is a part of the Church, very convenient and proper, and generally fitted and prepared for the Celebration of the Lord's Supper, which we call the <hi>Chancel.</hi> Here the <hi>Communion-Table</hi> may be placed, and the Communicants <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> with greater <hi>Order, Decency</hi> and <hi>Convenience</hi> for Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than in the <hi>Body</hi> of the Church, and the <hi>Seats</hi> there.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but you, <hi>My Brethren,</hi> are ſenſible of this and ſatisfied in it, finding great <hi>inconvenience</hi> in Conſecrating in ſo ſtrait a place as an <hi>Ally</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and delivering the Bread and Wine in narrow <hi>Seats,</hi> over the Heads, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the Feet of thoſe that Kneel; When by removing into the <hi>Chancel</hi> at the time of that <hi>Solemnity,</hi> every one may Kneel without diſturbance, and receive with eaſineſs, and ſee the whole Office performed.</p>
            <p>This is ſo <hi>proper</hi> and ſo <hi>becoming,</hi> that one cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the Pariſhioners in any place ſhould be averſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament in this Order, and that <hi>Rectors</hi> as well <hi>Impropriate</hi> as <hi>Propriate,</hi> ſhould not take more care to fit their <hi>Chantels</hi> for this purpoſe, but that ſome lie wholly diſuſed, in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96907:13"/>more naſtie manner than any Cottager of the Pariſh would keep his own Houſe: Others are imployed for keeping School, by reaſon of which, the <hi>Seats, Pavement,</hi> and <hi>Windows</hi> are commonly broken and defaced, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion other rudeneſſes and undecencies which are not fit to be permitted in a place ſet a part for God's Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Reaſon</hi> that ſome give (as I have been informed) why they except againſt the uſe of the <hi>Chancel</hi> at the time of Celebrating the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> is ſtill more to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at; They lay it is <hi>Popery,</hi> and that Miniſters that uſe their Chancels for this office are <hi>Popiſhly</hi> inclined: But why <hi>Popery?</hi> Is it becauſe the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation made uſe of the <hi>Chancel</hi> to ſay <hi>Maſs?</hi> So they uſed the Body of the Church to perform other parts of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Service, and for that Reaſon they may as well except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſe of the <hi>Church</hi> for Reading the Scriptures and Preaching, as againſt the uſe of the Chancel for Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Communion; and there want not thoſe who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Argument ſo far as to cry down the uſe of <hi>Churches</hi> in general; But how weak and how unreaſonable is this? What if the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prieſt ſaid <hi>Maſs</hi> at the Altar in the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> may not the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for that reaſon perform the <hi>Communion</hi> Service there without the Imputation of <hi>Popery?</hi> If there be any <hi>Popery</hi> it muſt be in the <hi>Communion Office,</hi> and if that have any thing of <hi>Popery</hi> in it, why do they receive the Communion in the <hi>Church?</hi> If it have not, why may they not receive it in the <hi>Chancel?</hi> For there cannot be <hi>Popery</hi> in the <hi>Fabrick,</hi> nor in the <hi>Seats,</hi> or <hi>Table;</hi> it muſt be in the <hi>Office,</hi> or no where; and one may ſafely affirm that no Man can prove it to be there.</p>
            <p>But the uſe of the <hi>Chancel</hi> for the Communion Service is ſo far from being <hi>Popery,</hi> that the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Popish Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators</hi> in <hi>England</hi> permit the <hi>Chancels</hi> where they are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96907:13"/>concerned, to lie the moſt diſorderly and ruinous of any other, as I my ſelf have ſeen in ſeveral places; they are not careful to <hi>repair</hi> or <hi>clean</hi> them; nor can they be brought to contribute to the <hi>Reparation</hi> of Churches, but by meer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, and they would be well enough ſatisfied to ſee all the <hi>Chancels</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>England</hi> lye in <hi>Ruin,</hi> for this would be the moſt certain way to overthrow the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and bring in <hi>Popery,</hi> which being planted again by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> would ſoon oblige that Party to rebuild the <hi>Churches.</hi> This I thought not improper to mention, concerning this matter, upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Preaching;</hi> under this Head I compriſe <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> which was an early Practiſe in the Church of Chriſt and of great uſe for the Inſtructing of the younger ſort, and prepare them thereby both for <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and Receiving the <hi>Holy Communion.</hi> If you conſult the LIX. Canon, you will ſee that you are bound to this Duty of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing,</hi> under the Cenſures of ſharp <hi>Reproof</hi> firſt; and upon willingly offending again of <hi>Suſpenſion;</hi> and upon the contemptuous continuance in the neglect of it, of <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</hi> So careful and ſo concerned has the <hi>Church</hi> been in this method of <hi>Inſtruction</hi> or <hi>Preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But a <hi>ſincere</hi> and well deſigning Man would chearfully diſcharge this Duty though there was no Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> to inforce it; for he would conſider that as the time of <hi>Youth</hi> is the moſt proper time to begin <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> ſo <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing</hi> is the moſt <hi>proper</hi> way to <hi>inſtruct</hi> them in <hi>Religion;</hi> It is the Age in which they learn Arts and Sciences, and how do they learn them, but by the frequent and familiar <hi>Inſtructions</hi> of their Maſters, <hi>examining, repeating, inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and <hi>explaining,</hi> as there is occaſion and capacity for it? After the ſame manner muſt they be taught the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of Religion which are contained in the <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> It is not ſufficient that they <hi>Repeat</hi> the Words by Heart, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96907:14"/>they ſhould be taught the <hi>meaning</hi> alſo; and this cannot be done but by explaining the ſeveral Heads more copiouſly, and in the moſt eaſie and familiar manner; And he that is ſenſible of this, and of the Duty that he owes to the <hi>Children</hi> of his Pariſh, as well as to the <hi>elder</hi> ſort, would no more fail to <hi>Catechiſe</hi> than he would to <hi>Preach;</hi> for he knows that he ought to Feed as well with <hi>Milk,</hi> as with <hi>ſtrong Meat,</hi> and as a Faithful Steward, to give the <hi>Children,</hi> as well as the reſt of the Family, their proper and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Luk. 12.42.</note> proportionable Diet.</p>
            <p>And here I may fitly take occaſion to acquaint you, That I would not willingly <hi>Confirm</hi> any Children but ſuch as have been Inſtructed in the fore-mentioned manner, and ſuch as you your ſelves believe to have a <hi>competent</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Principles</hi> of Chriſtianity; This Knowledge muſt not be meaſured by their <hi>Age,</hi> nor by their <hi>ready utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of the Words of the Catechiſm, but by their <hi>capacity</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> to anſwer ſuch Queſtions, and to render ſuch an account of their Faith, as, you may hope, proceeds from a right Apprehenſion, and true Underſtanding of the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the Catechiſm. And therefore I muſt earneſtly deſire you to take more than ordinary Pains, before the times of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> and that not only in the <hi>Church,</hi> but, if need be, at your own <hi>Houſes</hi> alſo, to <hi>examine</hi> and <hi>inſtruct</hi> the riper ſort, that they may know what they are to do, and what they undertake at their <hi>Confirmation;</hi> and to give me a Note of the <hi>Names</hi> of ſuch as are ſo qualified and prepared; and for the younger and more ignorant, it is beſt to adviſe them to ſtay till another opportunity.</p>
            <p>There are other ways and methods of <hi>Preaching,</hi> (as it may in a general Senſe be called) namely, private <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and <hi>Admonition;</hi> Reſolving <hi>Doubts and Caſes</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; <hi>Comforting</hi> the afflicted; Furniſhing the Poor with <hi>Bibles</hi> and other good <hi>Books;</hi> directing the Richer ſort what <hi>Books</hi> to provide for their own uſe, and the uſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96907:14"/>of their Familyes, of which (God be thanked) this Age has produced many; Giving, or Lending to all ſorts of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> (there being no other way of preaching to them) ſuch <hi>Books</hi> as have been written on purpoſe to prevail with them to return to the Communion of this Church; particularly the <hi>Quakers,</hi> whoſe groſs <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemys</hi> have been <hi>detected</hi> and <hi>confuted</hi> ſo plainly by a late learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<note n="*" place="margin">Author of the Snake in the Graſs.</note> Writer, that if they be ſo ſincere as they generally pretend, they will be obliged to <hi>renounce</hi> them. Not that this can be expected from the <hi>Leaders</hi> of that Party; they have Ends to ſerve in the Conduct of that deluded People that will ingage them to <hi>adhere;</hi> notwithſtanding Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Conviction too; But I hope the Simple and well-meaning may be brought to ſee their Errors, and forſake them, if the
<note n="b" place="margin">Satan diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rob'd.</note>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Inſtitution of Water-Baptiſm.</note> 
               <hi>Books</hi> of this Author were put into their hands, and that they could be prevailed with to read them, or to hear them read.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Head of <hi>Preaching</hi> I muſt remind you of a particular <hi>opportunity</hi> you have, and a very <hi>advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> one, of performing ſome parts of this Duty; which is, at the <hi>Viſitation of the Sick;</hi> for which there is a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Office</hi> appointed; In this, the <hi>Exhortation</hi> is very <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> and <hi>ſerious,</hi> and the <hi>Collects</hi> very affecting; and if it be performed whileſt the Sick Perſon is capable of <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>joyning</hi> in it, may be of great uſe and Benefit; But either the Sick Perſon or the Relations are generally too negligent in giving <hi>timely</hi> notice, ſo that it has not always that good Effect which otherwiſe it might; But when it is known that People are ſick, they ought diligently to be <hi>viſited,</hi> that when they have leaſt <hi>ability</hi> of their own, by reaſon of their Weakneſs or Pain, or fear of Death, or puniſhment after Death, they may be <hi>ſuccoured</hi> and <hi>aſſiſted</hi> by the help of others; This is the time when the Devil, the malicious and watchful
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96907:15"/>Enemy of our Salvation, has great opportunity of tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deceiving Men, either by <hi>Preſumption</hi> or <hi>Deſpair;</hi> this therefore is an apt time for you to <hi>reſiſt</hi> him, and to reſcue the Souls committed to your Care under ſo great a Danger; Beſides, this <hi>Office</hi> duly performed may be of good uſe not only to ſick and dying Perſons, but alſo to Relations and Viſitors, who may happen to be preſent, and to the Miniſter himſelf; who, if he have a ſerious Sence of things cannot but improve himſelf in diſcourſing with Perſons in that condition; upon all which accounts this <hi>Office</hi> ought not to be neglected.</p>
            <p>And here I conclude what I thought fit to ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Preaching,</hi> which if you would purſue thorough all the forementioned inſtances of it, with a <hi>ſincere</hi> and honeſt heart, and a fervent deſire of doing all the good you can, you would contribute to the upholding of the Kingdom of Chriſt in this Age of Atheiſm, Infidelity, and Licentiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now conſider one other <hi>Office</hi> with which you are intruſted as you are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in which you are highly concerned to be <hi>faithful,</hi> and that is the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Matrimony.</hi> I am ſorry there are ſo many in this <hi>Church,</hi> and ſome in this <hi>Dioceſe,</hi> who abuſe their Truſt in this Matter. It is ſo preſumptuous, and ſo perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious a practice, that it cannot be cenſured too ſeverely. Such as can be tempted for a little Summ of Money, or a great one, to marry any Perſons that reſort to them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Publication</hi> of <hi>Banns,</hi> or <hi>Licenſe</hi> duly obtained, or with Licence at <hi>uncanonical Hours,</hi> and in a <hi>Clandeſtine</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, either in their own Houſes, or in their Churches, are not fit to be intruſted with ſuch a Power; They do an <hi>ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> and <hi>uncanonical</hi> Act knowingly and willfully, which they that have any ſence of their Character, and Truſt, and Duty to their Superiours, would not do: Eſpecially,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96907:15"/>ſuch as dare preſume to marry thoſe whom they <hi>know,</hi> or have reaſon <hi>vehemently</hi> to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> to be either <hi>ſtolen,</hi> or not to have the conſent of Parents, Guardians, or Friends; Theſe are the <hi>Peſts</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> of our <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> Their Greedineſs of Profit has debauched their Conſciences, and they have no feeling of their own Wickedneſs, nor any regard to the many evil Conſequences that attend this practice; as, the Ruine of the <hi>Branches</hi> of <hi>Noble Familys;</hi> Diſquieting <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Relatives,</hi> and alienating their Affections; Incouraging <hi>Diſobedience</hi> in Children; and that which is indeed the leaſt to be lamented, expoſing them ſelves to Ignominy, Contempt and Puniſhment; not to mention, what has ſometimes happened, <hi>legitimating,</hi> as much as in them lyes, <hi>Inceſtuous</hi> Mixtures. One would think that no conſidering Man of Conſcience and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, could be prevailed upon for a preſent Benefit to drive on ſuch a <hi>pernicious</hi> and <hi>diſhonourable</hi> Trade, and perſiſt in it, with defyance of all <hi>Admonition, Cenſure,</hi> and <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This I could not forbear to ſay out of that inſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation I have to this moſt <hi>treacherous</hi> and <hi>impudent</hi> Practiſe.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewed you how <hi>ſincerity</hi> of Heart, which is that <hi>Qualification</hi> which our Saviour preferred in chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> would diſpoſe you to the due and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar performance of all the Offices of your Holy Function; I ſhall now ſhew you how neceſſary this <hi>Qualification</hi> is for the Conduct of your <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sincerity</hi> would ingage us to live agreeably to our <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> which if we do not, our <hi>Preaching</hi> would be little regarded, ſo that our Miniſtry would be in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ineffectual, and unprofitable. Men that behold the <hi>evil</hi> Converſation even of <hi>good</hi> Preachers, will be apt to ſay that either they do not <hi>believe</hi> the Doctrine <hi>they preach,</hi> or that the <hi>Practice</hi> of it is not ſo neceſſary to Salvation as they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96907:16"/>repreſent it; for they that preſs an holy <hi>Converſation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, in order to the <hi>ſaving</hi> of their <hi>Soules,</hi> one would think, if they meant ſincerely, would not be negligent, by the ſame way, to <hi>ſave</hi> their <hi>own;</hi> ſo that they muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily fall under the cenſure of being either <hi>unfaithful</hi> Guides, or <hi>inſincere</hi> Believers.</p>
            <p>Thoſe keene Expoſtulations of St. <hi>Paul</hi> directed to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daizing Chriſtians at <hi>Rome,</hi> as they could not fail to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> or <hi>confound</hi> thoſe Offenders, ſo they and others of the like nature, may be made uſe of to the ſame purpoſe, to ſuch Preachers of the Goſpel, as walk not according to the Goſpel. <hi>Romans</hi> 2d. 21. <hi>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doeſt thou ſteal? Thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, doeſt thou commit Adultery? Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doeſt thou commit Sacriledge?</hi> So St. <hi>Paul.</hi> To which, if we add, Thou that preacheſt the Laws of <hi>Purity,</hi> and <hi>Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> &amp;c. Art thou guilty of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>Exceſs,</hi> or <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> or <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Contention,</hi> or <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of Authority? What Reply could the Offenders make? If they do not preach theſe Doctrines, they neglect to <hi>inſtruct</hi> Men in their Duty; and if they doe preach them, and doe not lead their Lives accordingly, they fail in their <hi>Practiſe;</hi> So that they who miniſter in <hi>holy</hi> things, and lead <hi>unholy</hi> Lives, are the moſt <hi>ſelf-convicted</hi> and <hi>ſelf-condemn'd</hi> Men in the World; They have nothing to ſay for themſelves, becauſe they do not onely <hi>know</hi> their Duty, but <hi>perſuade</hi> to the Practiſe of it, and yet doe not <hi>practiſe</hi> it themſelves. They <hi>Reprehend</hi> thoſe Vices in others, in which they <hi>indulge</hi> themſelves. They tell Men they ſhall be <hi>damned</hi> for <hi>committing</hi> thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> which they themſelves <hi>commit.</hi> How <hi>inconſiſtent,</hi> how <hi>inſincere,</hi> and <hi>diſagreeable</hi> is this?</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96907:16"/>
            <p> But this is not all; The Miniſters of Chriſt are bound not onely to live according to the Laws of Chriſtianity in general; But they have a Law of their own, a Law <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> to the Officers of Chriſt's Kingdom, by which they are obliged to a <hi>ſtrictneſs</hi> and <hi>decorum</hi> ſuitable to that <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> has deſcribed the Particulars in his Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and occaſionally in other places, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo has done. There you may ſee by what <hi>meaſures</hi> you are to govern your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and your <hi>Familys,</hi> with reſpect to your Office and Character: Theſe indeed, were Men of the higheſt <hi>Station</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> in the Church, but the <hi>Inferiour</hi> and <hi>Subordinate</hi> as well as the <hi>Superiour</hi> are mentioned and deſcribed, and the Rules are much the ſame for both. I ſhall not need to tranſcribe them; it is a <hi>Mirroir</hi> you have in your own hands, and you may look daily into it, and compoſe your <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> by it.</p>
            <p>If I would ſingle any <hi>Particulars</hi> of thoſe many Offences, which the Miniſters of the Goſpel of all Ranks are there directed to avoid, it ſhould be thoſe of publick <hi>Scandal;</hi> not that theſe are in their own Nature Sins of greater <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity</hi> than ſome others there mentioned, but that the <hi>Conſequences</hi> may be worſe, and the <hi>Ignominy</hi> greater.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance, <hi>Intemperance,</hi> which is one of the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> mentioned by
<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 1. 3 c. 3 and 8 ver. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as it is a Sin that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers it ſelf more openly than many others, ſo there is no other that renders a Clergyman more <hi>ridiculous</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible,</hi> for which reaſon, if no other, it ought carefully to be avoided; But it infects the Neighbourhood too, and they that like it are the more incouraged to practiſe it by the <hi>example</hi> and <hi>converſation</hi> of their Preacher, which increaſes the <hi>Scandall.</hi> But though the <hi>Scandall</hi> be very great where the Guilt is manifeſt, and that the Offenders cannot be too ſeverely cenſured, yet if they be but few, as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96907:17"/>I hope they are not many, in compariſon of the great Body of the Clergy, the whole ought not to be reproached for the misbehaviour of thoſe few; Let the <hi>Scandall</hi> lye in its own place, and there let the Offenders be puniſhed by all the Penaltys <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Civil;</hi> But God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that the <hi>innocent</hi> ſhould ſuffer with the <hi>guilty,</hi> as they do too often, by the uncharitable and malicious <hi>hints, Suggeſtions,</hi> and groundleſs <hi>Storys</hi> of thoſe that are their Enemys, becauſe they demand their Dues, and <hi>tell them the Truth;</hi> An apparent offence of this nature in one Man has been known to occaſion the cenſure of many, eſpecially of thoſe who do not abridge themſelves the <hi>freedome</hi> of Converſation with one another, being not conſcious to themſelves of any unworthy <hi>deſigne</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> by ſuch Converſation; and yet even in this it muſt be ſaid, that there is regard to be had to <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place</hi> and other <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> ſo <hi>ſtrict</hi> and <hi>nice</hi> are the <hi>meaſures,</hi> by which the Clergy are to govern themſelves.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould inſtance in another ſcandalous Sinne men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is
<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 3.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> I know I ſhould gratify ſome Men who are apt to accuſe the <hi>Clergy</hi> too commonly in this Matter; but very unjuſtly; for I think I may truely ſay that there is no <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of Men, or at leaſt I know not any, that, in the common Body of them, are freer from this Sin then the <hi>Clergy</hi> are; inſomuch, that the greater number of them, it may be, ſtand in need of Advice to be more <hi>provident, conſidering their ſmall</hi> Incomes, <hi>and the great Payments</hi> with which they are <hi>conſtantly</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, and at ſome times <hi>unjuſtly</hi> oppreſſed; But true it is, that all cannot be excuſed, and it muſt needs be ſaid, that ſuch as are <hi>really</hi> guilty in this matter, are highly <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous.</hi> How <hi>unbecoming</hi> and <hi>reproachful</hi> is it for thoſe who ought, above all others, to have their <hi>Converſation in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> as being the Preachers of that Doctrine, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96907:17"/>from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and leads to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that expect their Rewards for ſo Preaching in <hi>Heaven,</hi> to <hi>mind earthly things</hi> immoderately, and ſtudy and practiſe that <hi>Wiſdom which is earthly?</hi> Such as they that are <hi>inſatiably</hi> greedy in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring and heaping up Preferments, or <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> in the uſe of thoſe they injoy, or incumber themſelves with the <hi>ſecular</hi> Affairs of other Perſons, imploying a great part of their <hi>tyme</hi> and <hi>labour</hi> in <hi>worldly</hi> Concernments which ſhould be imployed in the proper Buſineſs of their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but take notice of one Inſtance of <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> which I take to be very <hi>unworthy</hi> and <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> which is not allowing <hi>Curates</hi> a meet and competent Maintenance agreeable to their <hi>Education, Character,</hi> and the occaſion of their <hi>Expences.</hi> What a <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>ſordid</hi> thing is it for Men of <hi>great</hi> Preferments to <hi>cheapen</hi> Curates, and contract with them for 20, or 25, or 30 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> (for they ſeldom exceed that proportion, calling it a <hi>Competency</hi>) when according to the value of their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Incomes they might make it <hi>double</hi> to that? Then they might be provided of more <hi>ſufficient</hi> Curates then ſome of them are. This is a very <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Practiſe, and makes <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Curates.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not proceed to inſtance in any other particulars of <hi>Scandall,</hi> theſe 2 of <hi>Intemperance</hi> and <hi>Worldlymindedneſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> as being the moſt <hi>expoſed</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> where they are practiſed.</p>
            <p>But though the <hi>Scandall</hi> in both be very great, the <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous</hi> are not ſo numerous as ſome ill-principled and evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded People, who are prone to <hi>cenſure</hi> at randome, would repreſent them to be. God be thanked that it may be affirmed truely, that the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> in general, are not only good Preachers, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and good Men, and the <hi>freedome</hi> which ſome are apt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96907:18"/>to accuſe them of proceeds not from <hi>vicious</hi> Inclinations but from an abhorrence of <hi>Hypocriſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall add no more to what I have ſaid concerning your <hi>Behaviour,</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> but onely this, that though the <hi>Rules</hi> be <hi>more,</hi> and <hi>ſtricter</hi> relating to the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> than to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in general, yet thoſe that are <hi>ſincere</hi> will make it their Endeavour to live up to them; <hi>Sincerity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Principle that will not permit a Man to <hi>ſhift off</hi> any Duty, whether <hi>active</hi> or <hi>paſſive,</hi> though never ſo <hi>hard,</hi> which is laid upon him by God, or which he lays upon himſelf; for which reaſon, as I told you at the beginning, our Saviour made choice of honeſt upright Men, as the moſt ſuitably qualified to be the <hi>Officers</hi> of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And here it may not be improper to ſuggeſt to you, That this Principle of Sincerity would prevent a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Failings</hi> and <hi>misbecoming</hi> Practices in ſome of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> which though they ſeem not of ſo great <hi>Malignity</hi> as thoſe I have mentioned, yet ought to be taken notice of, and regulated,</p>
            <p>One is concerning the ſubſcribing <hi>Teſtimonials</hi> of ſuch as apply themſelves for Orders or Inſtitutions, in which, to my <hi>own</hi> Knowledg, ſome of the Clergy of <hi>this Dioceſe</hi> have been too eaſie; and though they may call it <hi>Charity,</hi> it is a great miſtake; for by this means the Biſhop, who can know nothing of the Converſation of Men, but by the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of thoſe who do know, is often <hi>deceived,</hi> and ſo unworthy Men creep into Orders, to the diſhonour of their <hi>holy</hi> Profeſſion; which indeed is to be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>unfaithfulneſs</hi> of thoſe that ſet their hands to <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials,</hi> either <hi>blindly,</hi> having no knowledg of the Perſon; or <hi>falſly,</hi> knowing that he is not worthy of the Character they give of him.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96907:18"/>
            <p> To which may be added that of granting <hi>inſufficient, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonical,</hi> and <hi>falſe Titles</hi> to Curates, when thoſe that grant them never intend to imploy them as <hi>Curates,</hi> or to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> but only to give them an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of entring into <hi>Orders,</hi> and then let them <hi>ſhift</hi> for themſelves; and indeed this has occaſioned a great deal of <hi>ſhifting,</hi> ſome being forced to take up with <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>poor</hi> conditions and ways of Livelihood, and others wandring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for Imployment, and even craveing <hi>Charity,</hi> to the great contempt and diſhonour of their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Failing</hi> I ſhall inſtance in, is the not <hi>Repairing</hi> timely, the <hi>Chancels</hi> and <hi>Buildings</hi> belonging to <hi>Rectorys</hi> and <hi>Vicarages;</hi> by reaſon of which Neglect ſuch Buildings become ſo <hi>dilapidated</hi> that the yearly <hi>Profits</hi> of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice cannot ſuffice for the Charges of the <hi>Reparation;</hi> and that which renders this neglect more <hi>miſchievous,</hi> is, that ſuch Dilapidators many times die inſolvent, and ſo leave the whole <hi>Burden</hi> of the Repair upon the <hi>Succeſſour;</hi> which if he undertake to do ſubſtantially, as he ought, he muſt live ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>inconveniently</hi> in the mean time. Now what <hi>honeſty</hi> is there in this for a Man to injoy the whole <hi>Profits</hi> of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, it may be, for many years, and by neglecting to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire</hi> the Edifices belonging to it, leave an unſupportable Charge to a <hi>Succeſſor</hi> who muſt be forced to expend Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys in repairing before he receive any <hi>Proſits?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like <hi>Prejudice</hi> happens to Succeſſors in another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in which many Clergymen are <hi>culpable;</hi> which is the neglect of paying <hi>Tenths, Penſions, Procurations,</hi> and other <hi>Duties</hi> chargeable upon their <hi>Preferments.</hi> I am ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Clergy cannot receive their own Dues in ſome places, though they proceed fairly and legally to recover them. Many <hi>delays</hi> and <hi>evaſions</hi> are uſed in this caſe; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they cannot anſwer the <hi>neglect</hi> of paying the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Dues, both as it is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Duty to <hi>render to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96907:19"/>all their Dues,</hi> and as they are lyable by the neglect to very great Penalties.</p>
            <p>I have been much troubled to obſerve ſo great an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear</hi> of Tenths in this Dioceſe, where it is my Duty to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them. It is my earneſt Deſire that for your own <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> you would haſten the payment of the preſent <hi>Arrear,</hi> for which purpoſe I ſhall appoint one in my Viſitation to receive them and give Acquittances, which may be of ſome eaſe to you; and for the future, I muſt adviſe you to make more <hi>timely</hi> and <hi>punctual</hi> payment. The neglect of this has run ſome Benefices into ſo great an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear,</hi> that Clergymen are diſcouraged from taking <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to them, ſo that they continue ſeveral Years under <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration,</hi> in which ſtate, the <hi>Church</hi> and other <hi>Buildings</hi> become <hi>dilapidated,</hi> the <hi>Tythe</hi> in a great meaſure unpaid and loſt, the <hi>Gleab</hi> untilled and purloyned, the Patrons <hi>Right of Preſenting</hi> extinguiſhed, and the Benefice at laſt turned into a <hi>ſine cure.</hi> So great a miſchief has been occaſioned, only by the neglect of paying <hi>Tenths</hi> in due time. <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Honesty</hi> would have prevented this.</p>
            <p>Another Neglect, with which I ſhall conclude, is that of <hi>not Reſiding</hi> upon Benefices; which is an Omiſſion of very ill <hi>Conſequence,</hi> and occaſions great <hi>Complaint.</hi> Not only the Canons of <hi>General Councells,</hi> but the <hi>Provincial</hi> Canons allowed in this Kingdom are very <hi>ſtrict</hi> in this Caſe, and where they are not altered or limited by <hi>Statute</hi> Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in force, according to the Opinion of many Learned <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Lawyers,</hi> though ſome are of another Opinion; and the xli <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Convocation</hi> in 1603, though it ſuppoſes Licenſes of <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> for the keeping of <hi>more</hi> Benefices with cure than <hi>one,</hi> yet it ordains many <hi>Reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> and <hi>Limitations,</hi> which, if they were duely obſerved, would prevent many of thoſe ill Conſequences and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of <hi>non-reſidence;</hi> But Men have found out <hi>Evaſions</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96907:19"/>for theſe <hi>Reſtrictions,</hi> with which, however they may <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy</hi> themſelves, they do not <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the plain deſign and meaning of the <hi>Canon,</hi> and <hi>Sincerity</hi> would Remedy the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect if the <hi>Law</hi> cannot.</p>
            <p>I have now no more to add, but only to deſire you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably to receive theſe <hi>Advices</hi> which proceed from that <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> Intention, which I have here <hi>recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> And I beſeech Almighty God ſo to <hi>impreſs</hi> them upon your Hearts, that I may ſee a good <hi>Effect</hi> of them. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>John Everingham,</hi> at the Star in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> near the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Houſe of Lords at the <hi>Abbey-Church</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s-<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 11th of <hi>December,</hi> 1695. being the Day appointed for a Solemn Faſt and Humiliation. By the Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, <hi>James,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Houſe of Lords at the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey-Church</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s-<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. being the Anniverſary of the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. of Glorious Memory. By the Reverend Father in God, <hi>William,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litchfield,</hi> Lord Almoner to His Majeſty.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96907:20"/>
            <p> A Sermon Preach'd before the Houſe of Lords at the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey-Church</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 30 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1691. being the Martyrdom of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. By the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in God, <hi>Humphrey,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bangor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Guide of a Chriſtian, directing him to ſuch Things, as are by him to be Believed, Practiſed, Feared, and Hoped for. There are added at the End Prayers to be uſed on ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Occaſions. The Second Edition, carefully Corrected. Prince bound 6 <hi>d.</hi> This Book is deſign'd to be given, as Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, throughout all Pariſhes in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Declaration of the Senſe of the Arch-biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, now in and about <hi>London,</hi> upon the Occaſion of their Attendance in Parliament; concerning the Irregular and Scandalous Proceedings of certain Clergy Men, at the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sir <hi>John Friend,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Parkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Animadverſions on Two Pamphlets, lately Publiſh'd by Mr. <hi>Collier.</hi> The one call'd, A Defence of the Abſolution given to Sir <hi>William Parkins</hi> at the Place of Execution, <hi>Apr.</hi> 3. The other, A Vindication thereof; occaſion'd by a Paper, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, A Declaration of the Senſe of the Arch biſhops and Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Shewing the Nature of the late Abſolution, both as to Church and State. In a Letter to a Friend.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of Jacobitiſm; or Remarks upon a Dialogue between <hi>K.W.</hi> and <hi>Benting.</hi> In a Dialogue between two Friends of the Preſent Government.</p>
            <p>A Debate on the Juſtice and Piety of the preſent Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, under King <hi>William.</hi> In two Parts; The firſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the <hi>State,</hi> the ſecond to the <hi>Church,</hi> between <hi>Eucheres,</hi> a Conformiſt, and <hi>Dyſcheres,</hi> a Recuſant. By <hi>Samuel Hill,</hi> Rector of <hi>Kilmington,</hi> Author of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Abiathar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eight Sermons, preached on ſeveral Occaſions. By <hi>Nathaniel Whaley,</hi> Rector of <hi>Broughton,</hi> in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96907:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
